Hi, everyone in the Ubuntu community.
Hi~Ubuntu 社群的各位夥伴大家好
First of all, I am very grateful to UbuCon ASIA
首先非常感谢 Ubucon Asia 提供這個機會
for providing this opportunity for me to communicate with everyone
讓我與大家交流
Today I want to share with you
今天我想與大家分享
all the efforts that the openEuler community has made in the open source compliance area.
OpenEuler 社群在開源法規方面做出的一些努力
I hope that I can collide spark with everyone more.
希望能與各位碰撞出更多的思维火花
OpenEuler community was born at the end of 2019
OpenEuler 社群誕生於2019年末
and is currently the largest,
是當前中國原生的最大
most active and transparent operating system open source community in China.
最活躍、最透明的作業系統開源社群
.A total of three releases have been issued since the first version was released in March 2020,
自2021年3月發布第一個版本以来共發行3個發行版
and more than 6,000 community contributors have participated in.
目前已有超過6000名社群貢獻者參與其中
Kylin software I work for
我所供職的麒麟軟體
is the second largest contributor to the OpenEuler community.
是 OpenEuler 社群的第二大貢獻者
Open source compliance is a very big topic,
開源法規是一個非常龐大的話題
including but not limited to copyright and license compliance
包括但不限於 Copyright 和 license 法規
patent compliance, export control compliance,
專利法規 、出口管制法規
GDPR compliance, trade secret compliance
GDPR 法規 、商業祕密法規
and trademark compliance, etc.
商標法規等等
open source compliance is also a breakthrough to encourage developers
了解開源法規也是鼓勵開發者了解開源文化、加入開源社群的突破口
to understand the open source culture and join the open source community.
了解开源合规也是鼓励开发者了解开源文化、加入开源社区的突破口
OpenEuler community has placed great emphasis on open source compliance since its creation
OpenEuler 社群自創建開始便非常重視開源法規工作，
With the rapid development of the community,
随着社群的快速發展
a special compliance sig was established in January 2021.
於2021年1月成立了專門的法規 SIG
The main work content includes
主要工作内容包括
research and science popularization in compliance-related fields,
法規相關領域的研究和科普
analysis and answers to community compliance problems,
社群法規疑難問題的分析解答
and development and maintenance of the access control system when submitting community contributions.
以及開發維護提交社群貢獻時門禁系統中的法規檢查工具
response to the most core license recognition management work in the open source community governance work,
針對開源社群治理工作中最核心的 license 識別管理工作
the compliance sig has designed and planned a complete set of compliance tool chains,
法規 SIG 設計規畫了一套完整的法規工具鍊
and is now steadily advancing the implementation according to the roadmap.
目前正按照 roadmap 穩固推進實現
Combining the specific functions of the various link tools,
结合各個環節工具的具體作用
the compliant sig partners named them after the names of famous people in the ancient Chinese Three Kingdoms period.
法規 SIG 的夥伴以中國古代三國時期著名人物的名稱為他們命名
Every fan of the Three Kingdoms will smile when they hear their names.
每一位三國迷聽到這些名字都會會心一笑
Next, I will explain the complete operation process of the entire tool chain for everyone.
下面，我將為大家講解整個工具鏈的完整運轉流程
When the community receives a new pr,
當社群收到新的 PR 時
we first ask the Cao Chong tool to classify the submitted content into code or non-code
我們首先請出“曹冲”工具將提交内容分類為程式碼類和非程式碼類
such as documents, multimedia， rich text, etc.
如文檔，多媒體，富文本等
Text documents can be directly scanned for their license information,
文本文檔可直接掃描其 license 訊息
while code types need to be used Huatuo Code Kinship Analysis tool analyzes its kinship
而程式碼類則需使用“華陀”工具對其進行血缘分析
and scans for fragment references of existing open source software source codes.
掃描是否有現有開源軟體原始碼的片段引用
.If there is a reference, confirm whether it complies with the corresponding license.
如存在引用，則確認其是否遵從了對應的 license
If there is no license, manual judgment is required to determine whether there is plagiarism.
若沒有 license，則需人工判定是否存在抄襲行為
Because of the severe conditions of this stage,
因為此環節的嚴苛條件
the tool was named Zhang Fei, a man who is the gateway, ten thousand men cannot open.
該工具被命名為“一夫當關萬夫莫開”的“張飛”
After Zhang Fei Gatekeeper access control is passed,
“張飛”門禁通過後
a standard license text comparison is required to confirm
還需進行 license 標準文本比對
that it is the standard version of the license text or a variant license modified by the developer.
確認其是標準版本的 license 文本還是開發者修改過的變種license
For all the licenses involved in the project,
針對項目涉及到的所有 license
uniformly check the SPDX standard format,
統一對其進行 SPDX 標準格式校驗
and then confirm whether each license has passed the OSI or FSF certification.
之後確認各 license 是否通過了 OSI/FSF 認證
.If it is not OSI or FSF certified license,
如果是非 OSI/FSF 認證的license
a community decision is required.
需要社群决策是否同意引入
Next, the Diao Chan system will determine whether the labels of different licenses are compatible or conflicting.
接下来，“貂蟬”系統將判定不同 license 的標籤是否兼容或衝突
the compliance risk analysis report of the entire project is formed
最終形成整個項目的法規風險分析報告
and output to the SBOM risk warning board and archived.
輸出至 SBOM 風險預警看板並存檔
Developers and reviewers can check the compliance risk summary of the entire project through the SBOM risk pre-warning board
開發者和評審者可以通過 SBOM 風險預警看板查閱整個項目的法規風險總結
and at the same time can open a detailed examination of the project’s explicit and implicit dependencies,
同時可展開詳細查閱該項目的顯示依賴和隱式依賴 license
and confirm whether the omissions are in the abrupt license.
確認是否存在遺漏、衝突等問題
.The name of the Diao Chan system Diao Chan is one of the four great beauties in ancient China.
“貂蟬”系統的名稱“貂蟬”，是中國古代四大美女之一
With a friendly human-computer interface, the system summarizes boring legal texts into three types of
該系統以友好的人機互動界面，將枯燥乏味的法律文本總結歸納為
labels for rights, obligations and restrictions for users to quickly identify and understand various common licenses.
權利、義務和限制三類標籤，供用户快速識別了解各類常見 license
The Diao Chan system also provides an API interface for the access control system or a third party to use.
“貂蟬”系統同時也提供了 API 接口供門禁系統或第三方使用，
Developers can use the GraphQL API provided by the Diao Chan system to conveniently confirm the interface information.
開發者可以使用“貂蟬”系統提供的graphQL方式的 API，方便的確認接口訊息
At present, we have mainly completed the development of the Diaochan system and Huatuo tools.
目前我们主要完成了“貂蟬”系統與“華陀”工具的開發
Zhangfei Gatekeeper has also been put into trial operation,
“張飛”門禁也已投入試營運
and there are still many tasks waiting for us.
還有許多工作等待著我们
The current entire compliance tool chain considers common problems in license compliance work,
當前整個法規工具鏈考慮了 license 法規工作中常見的
such as  whether to declare a license,
是否聲明 license
whether the license text is standard,
license 文本是否規範
and whether the license used has been certified by OSI or FSF,
使用的 license 是否經過了 OSI/FSF 認證
is the license in the project fully compatible
項目中的 license 是否完全兼容沒有衝突等常見問題
there is still a huge room for improvement
但還存在極大的改進空間
I hope that friends in the Ubuntu community will share your valuable opinions with us.
希望 Ubuntu 社群的各位朋友向我們分享你的寶貴意見。
Thank you all, goodbye!
謝謝大家!再見!